Hello, and welcome to this compliance review screencast for Verdent —
a YouTube video search and analysis tool.
Verdent is built on top of the YouTube Data API v3.
This recording demonstrates how our application accesses and displays YouTube API data.
This demonstrates compliance with YouTube's API Services Terms of Service
and Developer Policies.
Verdent is a single-page web application served by a FastAPI back-end.
Users can search for YouTube videos by keyword and apply various filters.
Available filters include: video duration, publication date,
category, language, and region.
All data displayed in this application comes exclusively from
the YouTube Data API v3. No data is scraped.
Let me demonstrate a live search.
I'll type the keyword "gaming" and hit Search.
The application calls the YouTube Data API search.list endpoint
with the keyword, video type, duration filter, and region code.
The search.list call consumes 100 quota units.
Results are ordered by view count.
The back-end then calls videos.list in batches of up to 50 IDs,
consuming only 1 quota unit per batch.
This retrieves full statistics for each video:
views, likes, comments, and duration.
The results are now displayed.
Each card shows the thumbnail, title, channel name, and key metrics.
For every video in the top-10 results, Verdent displays data
sourced directly from the YouTube Data API.
Thumbnail: from snippet.thumbnails.
Title: from snippet.title.
Channel: from snippet.channelTitle.
Subscriber count: from channels.list using statistics.subscriberCount.
View count: from statistics.viewCount.
Engagement Rate (ENG%) is calculated as viewCount divided by subscriberCount,
showing how well the video performs relative to the channel's audience.
Estimated Revenue is derived from industry-standard CPM ranges,
presented as a reference estimate only.
The trend analysis graphs visualise the distribution of views,
engagement rates, and publication dates across the result set.
All of this data is presented in real time from the API response.
No data is permanently stored in a database.
Let me highlight the API call optimisation built into the application.
First: quota awareness.
Each search.list call costs 100 units.
Each videos.list call costs 1 unit per batch of up to 50 videos.
The daily quota limit of 10,000 units is respected and monitored
via the /api/quota endpoint.
Second: server-side caching.
Results are cached for 30 minutes using an in-memory cache.
If the same search is repeated within 30 minutes,
the cached response is served immediately — zero additional API calls.
This dramatically reduces quota consumption for repeated queries.
Watch — the second search completes instantly.
Third: API key rotation.
If one key's quota is exhausted, the client rotates to the next key automatically.
This ensures uninterrupted service without manual intervention.
Every video result includes a direct link back to the original video on YouTube,
ensuring users can always access the authoritative source.
Channel information — subscriber counts and recent uploads —
is also obtained via the YouTube Data API channels.list endpoint.
Channel data is similarly cached for 30 minutes
to minimise redundant API calls.
Verdent helps content creators and marketers with market research,
identifying high-performing videos in any niche.
Revenue estimation: gauge monetisation potential based on engagement data.
Competitive analysis: compare channel performance across creators.
Trend identification: spot patterns in publication timing
and view velocity across search results.
All use cases rely solely on public data available
through the YouTube Data API v3.
In summary: we only call the YouTube Data API through official REST endpoints.
We do not scrape or redistribute raw API data.
All data is displayed in an aggregated, analytical context —
not as a substitute for YouTube.
Every video and channel links back to YouTube.
Quota usage is tracked, capped, and minimised through caching and batching.
Thank you for reviewing Verdent's YouTube API Services
compliance demonstration.
This concludes the Verdent compliance screencast.
For questions regarding API usage, please refer to the project repository.